Finding Aid for Detroit Japanese American Citizens League Records 1943-2005
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Detroit Japanese American Citizens League Records 1943-2005
Detroit Japanese American Citizens League.
2 oversize folders
17 oversize volumes
3 linear feet
9836 Bd 2, UBDm, UBDl
Detroit chapter of organization established to facilitate acceptance of Japanese Americans, to voice political concerns, and to provide social activities for its members. Records include chapter administrative records, event and outreach materials, publications, scrapbooks, and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The record group was donated by the Detroit Japanese American Citizens League in February 1998 and June 2012. Donor no. 8691
The collection is open for research.
The Detroit chapter of the Japanese American Citizens League (JACL) was established on June 17, 1946 after over 50 Japanese Americans relocated to Detroit from various war relocation camps. JACL had already been in existence since 1929 on the west coast, and as Japanese Americans sought new homes after their internment, many new chapters sprung up across the country. Initially led by Peter Fujioka, the chapter's first president, the Detroit chapter collaborated with others forming the Midwest District Council.
The national JACL organization has been responsible for changing the laws regarding citizenship, obtaining equal rights, abolishing derogatory labels, and publishing the Pacific Citizen a weekly newspaper for people of Japanese ancestry. However, the organization could not keep over 120,000 Japanese Americans living in the Western United States from being placed into war relocation camps in 1942 following the bombing of Pearl Harbor. The JACL fought the evacuation in court and also helped those interned relocate from the camps to communities in the Midwest and Eastern United States. In the early 1990s, mostly due to the ceaseless efforts of the national JACL and other organizations, former internees of the war relocation camps finally received redress payments of $20,000.
Although JACL was originally formed to facilitate the acceptance of Japanese Americans in the United States and act as a political voice, the group also organizes social activities. Events such as picnics, dinners, and dances, designed to attract more Japanese Americans to the group, are frequently held and social groups within JACL have formed such as the Junior JACL and Teen Clubs. Other educational activities such as lectures and special programs are also conducted.
Accomplishments of the Detroit chapter of JACL include funding the creation of the Japanese Room at Wayne State University in 1980, hosting of the 18th Biennial National JACL Convention in 1964, establishing the Detroit JACL Blood Bank, working on the Issei History Project, participating in the Detroit/Windsor International Freedom Festival and the Detroit Far Eastern Festival, sponsoring trips to Japan, and hosting a reception for the Muromachi Period Ink Paintings Exhibition at the Detroit Institute of Arts.
In 1996, Detroit JACL celebrated its 50th Anniversary. The celebration was marked with a special golden anniversary installation dinner and ball complete with greetings from Takeshi Kagami, Consulate General of Japan, Detroit and David Hayashi, JACL's Midwest District Governor, and a keynote address from George Takei, an actor whose best-known role was Captain Sulu on Star Trek.
Information for this section was obtained from "For Better Americans in a Greater America: The Story of the Japanese American Citizens League" located in Box 2, under Publications - National and the "Detroit Chapter JACL 50th Anniversary" publication found in Box 2 in the Events - Installation Banquets, Fiftieth folder.
The records of the Detroit Japanese American Citizens League (JACL) document the governance, concerns, initiatives, and activities of the Detroit JACL over the course of its history, beginning in the mid-1940s. The record group is arranged in eight series: Administrative Materials, Events, Outreach Activities, Publications, Related Organizations, Topical Files, Scrapbooks, and Photographs. Because the records are a compilation of materials donated from various JACL members, some duplication occurs among and within the series.
Subjects:
Detroit Japanese American Citizens League.; Japanese Americans--Ethnic identity.; Japanese Americans--Michigan.; Japanese Americans--Evacuation and relocation, 1942-1945.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Detroit Japanese American Citizens League.; Japanese Americans--Michigan.; Japanese Americans--Organizations--Michigan.; Japanese Americans--Social life and customs--Michigan.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Administrative Materials 1946-1996
  The Administrative Materials series contains various documents regarding the organization's governance and membership from the mid-1940s to the mid-1990s. It includes several versions of the chapter constitution, membership lists, and financial reports. Minutes, agendas, leadership lists, correspondence, and various other records can be found in the three "Mixed records" subseries. Additional administrative records may be found among the items filed in the "Miscellaneous" folders within the Topical Files series.
  - Constitutions
    - circa 1950-1960 (Box 1)
    - 1980-1981 (Box 1)
  - Membership
    - Lists 1946-1951, undated (Box 1)
    - Directory 1949 (Box 1)
    - List 1970 (Box 1)
    - Award 1983 (Box 1)
  - Mixed Records (meeting minutes and agendas, membership lists, announcements, correspondence, etc.)
    - 1951-1957 (Box 1)
    - 1961 (Box 1)
    - 1967 undated (Box 1)
    - 1968-1969 (Box 1)
    - 1970-1971 (Box 1)
    - 1977-1981 (Box 1)
    - 1982-1985 (Box 1)
    - 1985 (Box 1)
    - 1996 (Box 1)
  - Mixed Records 1980-1984
    (formerly in a binder)
    - Miscellaneous front material (Box 1)
    - Rosters (Box 1)
    - Board meetings (Box 1)
    - Scholarships (Box 1)
    - Building fund (Box 1)
    - Human rights (Box 1)
    - Redress (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous ending material (Box 1)
  - Mixed Records 1992-1996
    (formerly in binder)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - Board rosters (Box 1)
    - Minutes (Box 1)
    - Treasury (Box 1)
    - Directory (Box 1)
    - Special activity (Box 1)
    - Midwest District and National (Box 1)
  - President's Notebooks
    (handbooks for local presidents)
    - circa 1958 (Box 1)
    - circa 1968 (Box 1)
  - Treasurer's Reports
    - 1974-1981 (Box 1)
    - 1982-1990 (Box 1)
- Events 1949-2001
  The Events series consists of materials related to events organized for members of JACL from the late 1940s to the early 2000s. It includes both local events, such as reunion parties or the annual Installation Banquet, as well as regional and national JACL conventions hosted by the Detroit chapter.
  - Anniversary Celebration, 50th 1996 (Box 1)
  - Conventions hosted
    - Midwestern District Biennial 1951, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - National Convention 1964
      - 1000 Club Whing Ding Committee (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
      - Press Releases (Box 2)
      - Souvenir Booklet (Box 2)
      - Programs (Box 2)
    - Eastern District Council/Midwest District Council 1973 (Box 2)
  - Installation Banquets
    - Programs
      - 1953-1962 (Box 2)
      - 1963-1975 (Box 2)
      - 1978-1985 (Box 2)
    - Dinner/Dance 1954 (Box 2)
    - Committee Report 1967 (Box 2)
    - Fortieth 1986 (Box 2)
    - Forty-second 1988 (Box 2)
    - Forty-fourth 1990 (Box 2)
    - Forty-sixth 1992 (Box 2)
    - Fiftieth 1996 (Box 2)
  - Japan Tours 1972 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous invitations and programs 1949-1962 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous flyers and correspondence 1987-2001 (Box 2)
  - Reunion Parties 1986, 1989 (Box 2)
- Outreach Activities 1977-1996
  Examples of JACL's work with the greater community from the mid-1970s to mid-1990s, whether locally in Detroit or nationally, are documented in the Outreach Activities series. These include exhibits, the Far Eastern Festival of Detroit, the Japanese Room at Wayne State University, and writing letters to politicians in support of various pieces of legislation.
  - Exhibits
    - Peace Center 1992 (Box 2)
    - Planning materials/proposal circa 1996 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence 1996 (Box 2)
  - Far Eastern Festival of Detroit 1978, 1979, 1984 (Box 2)
  - Japanese American Curriculum Project 1980 (Box 2)
  - Japanese Community Cultural Building Committee 1977 (Box 2)
  - Japanese Room at Wayne State University
    - 1977-1980 (Contains blueprints) (Box 2)
    - 1980 1994 (Box 2)
  - Political correspondence
    - Redress Bill 1987-1988 (Box 2)
    - Civil Rights Act 1989 (Box 2)
- Publications 1947-2005
  The Publications series contains both local and national publications ranging in date from 1947 to 2005. Local items include issues of the Detroit JACL newsletter, as well as some related administrative materials. The nationally published materials include two historical booklets, a newsletter about membership statistics, and several brochures.
  - Local
    - Newsletters
      - The Nisei Detroiter 1947 (Box 2)
      - The Detroit JACL Newsletter (and variant titles)
        - 1953 (Box 2)
        - 1957 (Box 2)
        - 1958 (Box 2)
        - 1961 (Box 2)
        - 1962-1964 (Box 2)
        - 1980 1982 (Box 2)
        - 1985-1989 (Box 2)
        - 1990-1992 (Box 2)
        - 1993-1995 (Box 2)
        - 1996 2001 (Box 2)
        - Administrative material 1989-1993 (Box 2)
      - Aru Toki, 1966 (Box 2)
        (Jr. JACL)
  - National
    - "For Better Americans in a Greater America: The Story of the Japanese American Citizens League," 1951 (Box 2)
    - Membership Bulletin 1961 (Box 2)
    - Brochures circa 1970s, 1980s (Box 2)
    - "A Troubling Legacy: Anti-Asian Sentiment in America," 2005 (Box 2)
- Related Organizations 1949-1953
  Materials regarding the Mr. & Mrs. Club and the Nisei-Caucasian Fellowship during the late 1940s and early 1950s are found in the Related Organizations series. Although both had a strong relationship with JACL and likely shared many members with it, each maintained their own events and activities. The Mr. & Mrs. Club records focus on events and membership. The Nisei-Caucasian Fellowship records center on its monthly publication Beacon.
  - Mr. & Mrs. Club
    - Invitations and flyers 1949-1953 (Box 2)
    - Membership lists 1949-1952 (Box 2)
    - Mixed materials 1951-1952 (Box 2)
  - Nisei-Caucasian Fellowship
    - Beacon 1949-1950 (Box 2)
    - Beacon mailing lists, circa 1950 (Box 2)
- Topical Files 1943-1995
  The Topical Files series contains materials, dated from the mid-1940s to mid-1990s, on various topics related to JACL and Japanese American history. This includes the correspondence of Peter Fujioka, the chapter's first president, materials related to the Midwest District Council of JACL, and two folders related to aspects of World War II history. There is also a "Miscellaneous" subseries with materials organized by date range. These materials include correspondence and other documents that may be duplicated in the Events or Administrative Materials series.
  - Company History of the Antitank Company 442nd Infantry circa 1945 (Box 2)
  - Cooperative Services 1978 (Box 2)
  - Fujioka, Peter
    - Correspondence 1947-1972 (Box 2)
    - Luncheon Talk 1943 (Box 2)
  - Legacy Fund 1990-1991 (Box 3)
  - Midwest District Council
    - Oratorical Contest 1968 (Box 3)
    - Spring Business Meeting programs 1968 (Box 3)
    - Mixed materials 1980-1985 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous
    - 1947-1952 (Box 3)
    - 1949-1959 (Box 3)
    - 1960-1961 (Box 3)
    - 1960-1965 (Box 3)
    - 1967-1968 (Box 3)
    - 1972 (Box 3)
    - 1979-1987 (Box 3)
    - 1992-1995 (Box 3)
  - News Clippings
    - Chicago JACL Convention Murder 1970 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous 1945-1983 (Box 3)
  - Presidential Classroom for Young Americans 1984 (Box 3)
  - World War II Relocation 1943 (Box 3)
- Scrapbooks 1946-1973
  - Date-based
    The Scrapbook series most clearly demonstrates the activities of the Detroit JACL chapter from the mid-1940s to the mid-1970s. Most scrapbooks contain information about general chapter activities, while others focus on the activities of the youth groups or the golf club. Each book contains photographs and documentation of events and publications and has been kept intact if possible. Materials which have become detached have been transferred to folders. In addition, some photographs were removed from the scrapbooks for the exhibit entitled "From Manzanar to Motor City. A History of Michigan's Japanese American Community"; these are arranged in one folder and are labeled with a number designating which scrapbook originally contained the photograph. Some duplication appears between the scrapbooks and other series.
    - 1946-1950 (Volume 2)
    - 1950-1953 (Volume 3)
    - 1953-1954 (Volume 4)
    - 1954 (Volume 5)
    - 1955 (Volume 6)
    - 1957 (Volume 7)
    - 1969 (Volume 8)
    - 1970 (Volume 9)
    - 1971 (Volume 10)
  - Event or group-based
    - Biennial National Convention 1964 (Volume 11)
    - Junior JACL 1963-1966 (Volume 16)
    - Junior JACL 1972-1973 (Volume 12)
    - Motor City Golf Club 1949 (Volume 13)
    - Mr. & Mrs. Club 1946-1959 (Volume 17)
    - Teen and Children's Club 1957-1960 (Volume 14)
    - Teen Club 1959-1963 (Volume 15)
  - Loose items from scrapbooks
    - Photographs removed from scrapbooks for exhibit entitled "From Manzanar to Motor City. A History of Michigan's Japanese American Community," 1946-1992 (from various oversize volumes) (Box 3)
    - Photographs, 1958-1962 (from oversize volume 8) (Box 3)
    - Mr. & Mrs. Club
      - Event materials 1953-1959 (from oversize volume 17) (Box 3)
      - Sympathy materials 1957-1958 (from oversize volume 17) (Box 3)
    - Junior JACL
      - 1963 (from oversize volume 16) (Box 3)
      - 1964 (from oversize volume 16) (Box 3)
      - 1965 (from oversize volume 16) (Box 3)
      - 1966 (from oversize volume 16) (Box 3)
- Photographs, 1948-1994
  Photographs of installation banquets, picnics, conventions, teen events, and other activities from the late 1940s to the mid-1990s can be found in the Photograph series. Individuals in these photographs are mostly unidentified; however, the photographs are generally labeled and arranged according to event. Photographs stored in folders should be examined for identification markings on the back.
  - National Convention--Salt Lake City 1948 (Box 3)
  - Motor City Golf Club 1948-1957 (Box 3)
  - 1951 (from oversize volume 1) (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous 1951-1972 (Box 3)
  - Suki Yaki Dinner 1954 (Box 3)
  - Naturalization Class 1955 (Box 3)
  - Testimonial Dinner 1955 (Folder 1)
    (located in UBDm)
  - Spring Show--Urashima Taro 1963 (Box 3)
  - Biennial National Convention 1964 (Box 3)
    (see also oversize folder UBDl)
  - Midwest District Council Convention 1968 (Box 3)
  - Junior JACL 1972-1973 (Box 3)
  - Midwest District Council Convention 1973 (Box 3)
  - Japanese American Youths 1974-1975 (Box 3)
  - Albums
    - 1951 (Volume 1)
    - 1992-1994 (Box 3)